Guide to the John Marsh Wilcox Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Marsh Wilcox papers
1955-1990
1955-1983
SC0380
Wilcox, John M., (John Marsh), 1925-1983.
17 Linear feet
Correspondence, astrophysics papers, refereeing reports, lecture notes, travel records, reprints, research notes, films, and biographical materials, largely relating to his research and teaching.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Transferred from the Stanford Solar Observatory, 1990, and the Hansen Experimental Physics Laboratory, 2001.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
A solar physicist, Wilcox worked around the world studying the influence of solar magnetism on global weather patterns. A professor at Stanford University from 1971 to his death in 1983, he was also director of the Stanford Solar Observatory, 1973-1983.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, astrophysics papers, refereeing reports, lecture notes, travel records, reprints, research notes, films, and biographical materials, largely relating to his research and teaching.
Access Terms
Alfvén, Hannes, 1908-1995; Benson, Herbert, 1935-; International Sun-Earth Explorers.; Olson, Roger.; Roberts, Walter Orr.; Scherrer, Phillip H.; Severny, A.B.; Stanford Solar Observatory.; Stanford University. Department of Applied Physics. Faculty.; Svalgaard, Leif.; Wilcox, John M., (John Marsh), 1925-1983.; Willett, Hurd C. (Hurd Curtis), 1903-; Physics.; Solar activity.; Solar magnetic field.; Weather.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2001-319
  - NCAR – data, general (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NCAR, troughs – data, general, 1979-80; includes correspondence with Roger H. Olson (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sun Weather Workshop, 11-15 August 1980, notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sun Weather Workshop, related articles (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sun Weather Workshop, minutes and correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sun weather correspondence, 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sun Weather research ideas, including letter to Walter O. Roberts summarizing their meeting on troughs, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Troughs – new data (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Troughs – new data (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Maps, January 1967 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Maps, January 1967 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Maps, February 1967 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Maps, February 1967 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maps, February 1967 – computer printouts (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, A. Ebel, Jan. 9, 1978, re tape for 10-mb-height differences (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence re out-of-ecliptic space flight, 1972-74 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence re troughs, 1979 (Roger Olson, James G. Brasseur) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Monthly Weather Review, 3 issues from 1957 and 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Flattery, Tom, "Hough Functions," 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Characteristics of FGGE Level IIIA Data Sets from the NMC Global Data Assimilation System," draft June 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bergman, Kenneth, "A Multivariate Optimum Interpolation Analysis System for Temperature and Wind Fields," 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jenne, Roy, "Notes on NCM Analysis," 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Forecast analyses (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Viewer's Guide to the Film "The Solar X-Ray Corona," 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – 200mb (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – 300mb data (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – VAS 500 D16 to VAI 500 D30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – [no label] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – [no label] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – special weight factors (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – different key lists (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – more key lists (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sun weather notebook July 1976 – graphs (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – polarities (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – lags (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – trough times and sector boundaries (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – random polarities and epochs (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – IMF/VAI (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – data sets, files, and POLTEXT (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Troughs and IMF polarity notebook – loose items (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Unlabelled notebook – summary grand spe and 200mb SB133 grand spe (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Unlabelled notebook – 300mb SB133 grand spe and 300mb SB28A grand spe (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unlabelled notebook – 500mb SB133 grand spe, 500mb SB28A grand spe, and phase analysis (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Unlabelled notebook – morphology nature, 700mb SB133 grand spe, and SB28 A vs B (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Films:
    - Radio Hot Spots on the Quiet Sun (Bracewell) [16 mm] (Box 3)
    - Interplanetary Magnetic Fields, copy #7 and #10 [16 mm, color, 17 min.] (Box 3)
    - Solar Differential Rotation, Mt. Wilson Observations [16 mm] (Box 3)
    - Solar Differential Rotation, Eastern and Western halves –80 - +80 Lat., Aug. 1966-Mar. 1970, #1 and #2 [16 mm] (Box 3)
    - The Active Sun, McGraw-Hill Text-Films 657274 [16 mm, color] (Box 3)
    - Interplanetary Space, McGraw-Hill Text-Films 657273 [16 mm, color] (Box 3)
    - A New Look at the Sun, CSIRO Film Unit, Melbourne, [16 mm, color, 21 min.] (Box 3)
    - Newkirk Movie (in box labeled NCAR #121) [16 mm] (Box 3)
    - Solar Differential Rotation, Doppler Observations, Aug. 1966-Mar. 1970, Eastern and Western Hemispheres Displayed Separately [16 mm] – 2 copies (Box 3)
  - Data Tape:
    - USENIX 84.2 Distribution Tape #111, 1600 BPI [marked with note "obsolete"] (Box 3)
  - Films:
    - Solar Differential Rotation, Doppler Observations, Aug. 1966-Mar. 1970 [35 mm] (Box 4)
    - Solar Differential Rotation, Doppler Observations, Aug. 1966-Mar. 1970, Eastern and Western Hemispheres Displayed Separately [35 mm] (Box 4)
    - Unlabeled 35 mm film (not on a reel) that may be another Solar Differential Rotation film (Box 4)
  - Microfilms:
    - Preliminary Kitt Peak Photoelectric Solar Atlas of Solar Spectrum [35mm on extra large reel] (Box 4)
    - National Center for Atmospheric Research: (Box 4)
    - 5 reels for Svalgaard, Sequences 8239 (4/14/73), 8313 (4/14/73), 5700 (4/13/73), 8253 (4/15/73), and 5845 (4/14/74) (Box 4)
    - 1 reel for Astrik, Sequence 7744 (3/73) (Box 4)
    - 1 reel for Roy Jenne, Sequence 2236 (2/7/73) (Box 4)
    - 1 reel for F. Stanford, Sequences 5069, 5070, 5071, 5072, 5068, and 5073 (no date) (Box 4)